Preliminary Inventory of the Chester E. Finn, Jr. Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Chester E. Finn, Jr. papers,
1966-2000
78089
Finn, Chester E., 1944-
208 manuscript boxes (86.7 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Speeches and writings, memoranda, reports, correspondence, agenda, and printed matter, relating to education in the United States, and especially to educational policy during the presidential administrations of Richard M. Nixon and Ronald Reagan, and to activities of the Educational Excellence Network and of the United States National Assessment Governing Board.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
American educator; staff assistant to the president of the United States, 1969-1970; special assistant for education to the governor of Massachusetts, 1972-1973; United States assistant secretary of education for research and improvement, 1985-1988; director, Educational Excellence Network.
Scope and Content Note
Speeches and writings, memoranda, reports, correspondence, agenda, and printed matter, relating to education in the United States, and especially to educational policy during the presidential administrations of Richard M. Nixon and Ronald Reagan, and to activities of the Educational Excellence Network and of the United States National Assessment Governing Board.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-; Reagan, Ronald.; United States. Dept. of Education.; Educational Excellence Network.; United States. National Assessment Governing Board.; Education.; Education--United States.; United States--Politics and government.
Contents
- Teacher training and Teacher Corps (Box 1)
- Education in Massachusetts
- Educators, intellectuals, and ethnicity (Box 2)
- Health
- Population and family planning
- Council for Urban Affairs. Subcommittee on Education (Box 3)
- Scranton Commission on campus unrest
- Higher education #1 (Box 4)
- Higher education #3
- Higher Education Working Group (Box 5)
- James S. Coleman and school desegregation
- Campus unrest #2
- Youth (Box 6)
- "A Call for Cooperation," Presidential message to Congress, 1970
- Education in Massachusetts (Box 7)
- Urban Schools, decentralization, and school politics
- Higher education #2 (Box 8)
- Higher education #4
- Harvard Graduate School of Education A-400 Project (Box 9)
- Non-public schools and teachers' unions
- Writing by Daniel Patrick Moynihan (Box 10)
- Education (general)
- Black colleges (Box 11)
- Council for Urban Affairs. Subcommittee on Education
- Miscellaneous writings by Chester E. Finn, Jr.
- Presidential higher education message and follow-up, 1970 (Box 12)
- Educational research and Presidential message
- Education (research, Title I, funding, etc.) (Box 13)
- National Institute of Education #1
- National Institute of Education #2 (Box 14)
- Presidential elementary and secondary education message #2
- Presidential elementary and secondary education message #3 (Box 15)
- School finance
- Documents defining the project "The Improvement of High School Humanities Teaching" (Box 16)
- Correspondence
- Publicity
- Invitations to attend conferences
- Proposals for the conference "Improving High School Humanities Teaching," 1983. (Box 17-18)
  Includes list of public school-participants
- Participant packets for above conference (Box 18)
- Conference logistics/reservations
- Correspondence and memoranda to/from authors (Box 19)
- Participants (schools, colleges, teams)
- Correspondence to/from authors (Box 20-21)
- Participants
- Educational excellence network (Box 22)
- Against Mediocrity: The Humanities in America's High School, New York, 1984
- Writings during world trip, n.d. (Box 23)
- White House service, 1969-1970
- Personal correspondence at Vanderbilt, 1982 October-December
- Floor amendment to the Higher Education Reauthorization Bill, 1981 June 23
- Educational reform in Tennessee
- Correspondence (Box 24)
- Correspondence of Twenties Century Fund
- Report of the Task Force on Federal Elementary and Secondary Education Policy, 1983
- Service at UNESCO delegation
- Assistance to Ernest L. Boyer with his Carnegie High School study
- Personal correspondence while working in the Senate, 1977-1981 (Box 25)
- Correspondence while working at Vanderbilt, 1984
- Correspondence while working at Vanderbilt, 1981-1983 (Box 26)
- Correspondence while working for the Governor of Massachusetts, 1972-1973
- Overseers
- Correspondence with Daniel Patrick Moynihan, 1975-1977
- Old correspondence, 1970-1983
- Correspondence while working at Vanderbilt, 1981-1983 (Box 27)
- Lecture notes, American Social History, 1962-1963 (Box 28)
- Correspondence, 1966-1981
- "An Education in Administration: A Study of Five Graduate Schools and Their Implications for a Sixth," 1969 March, submitted by Chester E. Finn, Jr. (Box 29)
- "Community Participation in Title III Programs: The Newton and Boston Experiences," 1968 June, by Chester E. Finn, Jr.
- "A New Deal for Old Harbor: Public Housing in Boston, 1933-1937," prepared by Chester E. Finn, Jr.
- "Citizen Participation, School Planning and the Humboldt Avenue Experience," 1967 August 15, submitted by Chester E. Finn and Florence Shelton
- Schools, Health Care, and the Community: Final report of the Mission Hill-Parker Summer Study, Harvard Graduate School of Education, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1968 March, by John D. Herzog and Chester E. Finn, Jr.
- "The American High School: Educating for Tomorrow," Brown University, 1984 March 5-8
- Clippings
- Correspondence files - Hanna collection (Box 30)
- Correspondence - World trip, 1971 (Box 31)
- "Up Against the Wall, Brooks House!" Harvard University, 1968 August, by Chester E. Finn, Jr.
- "The Irish and the Boston Schools," 1870-1930, by Chester E. Finn, Jr.
- Correspondence while working at Vanderbilt, 1983-1985
- Educational excellence network, 1985 July (Box 32)
- Revised draft paper on "Television for Children," 1986 October (Box 33)
- United States. Department of Education - Memoranda, 1986-1987
- Briefing material and background information for site visitors for the School Recognition Program Meeting, 1988 February (Box 34)
- CLEI's involvement in adult literacy
- TOPS (Targeting Outstanding Programs and Schools)
- CLEAR (Center for Language Education and Research)
- Vocational Education Reauthorization Proposal
- Trade Bill
- ECIA working group
- United States. Department of Education. Office of Educational Research and Improvement, 1985-1988 (Box 35)
- United States. Department of Education - National Institute of education, 1985 (Box 36)
- United States. Department of Education - Centers competition, 1984-1987
- United States. Department of Education - Center on State and Local Policy Development and Leadership, 1985-1987
- United States. Department of Education - Leadership Center, 1987 (Box 37)
- United States. Department of Education - Center on Post-Secondary Teaching and Learning, 1985-1986
- United States. Department of Education - Information Service, 1985-1986
- National Library of Education, 1985
- United States. Department of Education - Association meetings, 1986-1988
- United States. Department of Education - ECIA Reauthorization, 1986-1987
- United States. Department of Education - Library Studies, 1985-1987 (Box 38)
- United States. Department of Education - MIS (Management Improvement Service), 1987
- Correspondence, Vanderbilt, 1981-1984
- United States. Department of Education - Publications policy, 1986
- United States. Department of Education - OERI Fellows Program, 1986-1987
- White House Working Group on Human Capital and Competitiveness, 1985-1986
- What Works II, 1986-1987
- USIA, Japan, etc., 1985
- United States. Department of Education - Public high schools, 1987 (Box 39)
- United States. Department of Education - Summary of the third Quarterly Report for the Regional Laboratory for Educational Improvement of the Northeast and Islands, 1986
- United States. Department of Education - Office of Educational Research and Improvement (OERI), 1985
- United States. Department of Education - Quarterly reports of the labs
- Programs for the improvement of practice, 1985-1986
- Secondary school recognition program, 1985-1988
- Youth-2000 Project, 1986 (Box 40)
- Youth indicators
- Zorinsky project, 1986
- Year of Elementary School, 1985
- Leadership in Educational Administration Development (LEAD) program, 1987
- National Council on Educational Research
- Correspondence
  - A
  - B-C (Box 41)
  - C-G (Box 42)
  - G-H (Box 43)
  - I-M (Box 44)
  - M-R (Box 45)
  - R-W (Box 46)
  - W-Y (Box 47)
  - A
  - A-B (Box 48)
  - B-C
  - C-E (Box 50)
  - E-M (Box 51)
  - M-P (Box 52)
  - P-S (Box 53)
  - S-T (Box 54)
  - T-Z (Box 55)
  - F-G (Box 56)
  - G-H (Box 57)
  - H-K (Box 58)
  - K-L (Box 59)
- FY Budget (Box 60)
  - 1987
  - 1988
  - 1989
  - 1990
- FY Budget 1987 (Box 61)
- FY Budget (Box 62)
  - 1988
  - 1989
  - 1990
- FY Budget (Box 63)
  - 1987
  - 1989
- Chronological file, 1986 (Box 64)
  - January-May
  - June-August
  - September-November
- Chronological file (Box 65)
  - 1986 December - 1987 February
  - 1987 March-April
- Chronological file, 1987 (Box 66)
  - May-July
  - August-October
  - November-December
- Chronological file, 1988 January-February (Box 67)
- OERI - Reauthorization
- OERI - Overview materials (Box 68)
- OERI - Reorganization highlights
- OERI - Reorganization, final version
- Advisory Council on Education Statistics
- Advisory Council on Education Statistics (Box 69)
- EL/SEC Redesign
- Reorganization - 1985 and beyond
- Advisory Council on Education Statistics (Box 70)
- Visclosky amendment
- Elementary/Secondary Redesign (working papers)
- National Assessment Planning Project, 1988 (Box 71)
- Elementary/Secondary Education Project
- National Assessment of Educational Progress (NAEP) (Box 72)
- NAEP material (Box 73)
- The Nation's Report Card: Improving the Assessment of Student Achievement
- NAEP material (Box 74)
- Hawkins-Stafford implementation
- Co-op program
- NAD evaluation of NCES
- Correspondence with Albert Shanker
- Standards
- Orientation Book for Participants in NAEP Conference, 1998 May (Box 75)
- President's Commission on Americans Outdoors, 1986
- Curricula vitae - A-H
- Curricula vitae - H-W (Box 76)
- Budget history (Box 77)
- Ipeds
- The Nation's Report Card: Improving the Assessment of Student Achievement
- Second Conference of the Study Group on National Assessment, 1986 September 30
- Third Conference of the Study Group on National Assessment, 1986 December 4
- Nation's Report Card press material, 1987 (Box 78)
- NAEP files
- Advisory Council of Education Statistics
- Plan for the Redesign of the Elementary and Secondary Data Collection Program (Box 79)
- NAEP files
- NAEP reading project
- OERI - Reauthorization (Box 80)
- OERI - Reorganization
- NCES plans (Box 81)
- NAEP plans
- OERI press kit
- NCES Renaissance (Box 82)
- OERI Reauthorization hearing - House of Representatives, 1986 February
- Data gaps
- CS - Council of Chief State Schools Officers
- Electronic mail
- Electronic mail (Box 83-88)
- Chronological file, 1988 (Box 89)
  - February 29-April 28
  - April 29-May
  - July-September
- Chronological file (Box 90)
  - June-September
  - October-December
- America 2000 - Candidate sites to illustrate proposed reports (Box 91)
- America 2000 - An education strategy
- America 2000 - An education strategy - A proposal for the President (Box 92)
- Briefing papers for Secretary Designate Alexander, 1991
- National Assessment Governing Board (Box 93-94)
- America 2000 - An education strategy (Box 95)
- America 2000 (Box 96)
- Alexander, Lamar
- National Assessment Governing Board (NAGB) (Box 97-107)
- Correspondence (Box 108)
  - A-C
  - D-J (Box 109)
  - K-Q (Box 110)
  - R-Z (Box 111)
- Correspondence - Individuals (Box 112)
  - A-B
  - B (Box 113)
  - B-C (Box 114)
  - C-E (Box 115)
  - E-H (Box 116)
  - H-I
  - K-M (Box 118)
  - M-O (Box 119)
  - O-R (Box 120)
  - R-S (Box 121)
  - S-Z (Box 122)
- Conferences and meetings on school reform (Box 123-124)
  - 1989-1990
  - 1990-1991 (Box 125)
  - 1991-1992 (Box 126)
- VITZ report (Box 127)
- Textbooks
- Correspondence
- Teacher education competition
- Vanderbilt University - Courses, 1989-1990
- Vanderbilt University - Interns, 1990 (Box 128)
- Democracy Reader
- Education for Democracy project
- Bradley Commission project
- Clippings
- Clippings (Box 129)
- National Academy of Education (NAE) project
- Meeting material, 1991 (Box 130)
- National Education Goals Panel, 1991-1992 (Box 131)
- NCEST
  - Standards Task Force
  - Origins and membership
- USIA Democracy project
- NGA - Aid project (Box 132)
- Civil rights
- Madison Center-College guide
- Radio America
- Twentieth century fund project
- Wisconsin project
- Williamsburg Charter - (John Seel) project
- Speeches on different educational issues (Box 133)
- Miscellaneous speeches (Box 134)
- Cedar
- Character
- Community colleges
- Curriculum
- Delivery system
- Educational choice
- Educational reform
- Handouts
- Higher education
- Reform, five fronts (variations before "six fronts")
- Social Studies
- Teaching, AACTE
- Bingaman (Senator) (Box 135)
- Testimonies
- Bill of rights "Free Country"
- AID Learning technologies project advisory panel
- Academic freedom
- American Council on Education - Higher education financing seminar
- California RUSH project
- NCSL project
- California summer reading list
- Advisory panel on children's issues
- Chicago school reform (Box 136)
- Chicago school reform project
- Choice
- Duc-le-to Fracas
- Disadvantaged Center (Box 137)
- Gagnon book - Publicity
- United States. Department of Education - History
- SSATB
- Correspondence (miscellaneous)
- England
- Current research (Box 138)
- Gramm/Rudman
- GAO
- First program
- First lessons reaction
- Fipse (Box 139)
- Finn - General
- Finn - Publications requested
- Finn - Invitations/Publications declined
- Facing history
- Heritage Foundation
- Globaloney
- Higher education - Assessment (Box 140)
- Excepted service
- IEA
- Globaloney
- Cedar (Box 141)
- Cannell, John
- Carnegie
- Book correspondence (Box 142)
- Book reviews
- Bilingual - GAO
- Blue ribbon panel
- The "Lake Woebegone" report
- Bilingual education (Box 143)
- Bartlett file
- American Council of Education - General
- Bennett - General
- Bennett speeches
- AERA speech
- AERA (Box 144)
- Review of the Department of Education's Institutional Eligibility and Accrediting Agency Recognition System, 1985
- Achievement - International comparisons
- Accreditation
- Institute for Educational Affairs (Box 145)
- Institute for Better Schools
- Humanities
- International Baccalaureate Office
- Information Services
- Illinois
- Institute for Educational Leadership (IEL)
- Library programs
- State Assistance Compacts/Labs
- Labs - Post-Lab Initiative (Box 146)
- Japan trip
- Japan - Correspondence
- Math and Science - Mathematical Sciences Education Board (MSEB)
- Mini-Centers Project
- NCES plans
- National Association of Secondary School Principals (NASSP)
- Joe Nathan/NCA
- NEH project - Conceptions of leadership (Box 147)
- N.D.N.
- NCES
- Pavac
- OERI personnel
- OECD (Box 148)
- NSF-ED cooperation
- NIE - The Bell years
- New book
- Polls
- OERI progress
- Peer Review Policy (Box 149)
- Principals (handbook)
- Secretary's Discretionary Fund
- Secretary's Research panel
- Sewall, Gil
- Son of what works
- Resumes
- State Education Statistics (Box 150)
- State Accountability
- Year-round education
- What works
- NAGB - History consensus (Box 151)
- NAGB Board Nominations, 1991
- National Assessment of Educational Progress in Geography, 1994 (Box 152)
- NAGB - Charter, FASA, Bylaws
- NAGB - Geography consensus
- NAGP materials (Box 153)
- NAGP Meetings, Conferences, Congresses (Box 154-155)
- Correspondence (miscellaneous) (Box 156)
- Waterford Institute
- PEPAC
- Charlottesville Education Summit
- National testing (Box 157)
- Achievement levels policy
- PEPAC (President's Education Policy Advisory Committee)
- Achievement levels - Printed matter (Box 158)
- NAGB - Board meetings
- NAGB - Board meetings (Box 159)
- National Education Goals Panel (Box 160)
- Walburg
- NAGB - Civics
- NAGB - NAEP Reauthorization (Box 161)
- Wurtz, Emily
  - General
  - Panel on criteria
- NAGB materials (Box 162-165)
- NAGB - Printed matter (Box 166)
- NAGB - Printed matter (Box 167)
- Math Results, 1992
- NAGB materials (Box 168)
- MDSH (Modern Red Schoolhouse) (Box 169)
- Hudson Institute
- Hudson Institute (MDSH) (Box 170)
- NAGB meetings (Box 171)
- Danzansky, Stephen I.
- NAGB meetings (Box 172)
  - 1993
  - 1992 (Box 173)
- America 2000 - An education strategy (Box 174)
- NAGB handbook
- National Assessment Covering Board - Policy book
- NAGB - Board meetings (Box 175)
  - 1994 November 17, 19
  - 1995 May 11-13
  - 1995 (Box 176)
    - March 3-4
    - August 3-5
- NAGB (Box 177)
  - General
  - New future
- Applications, 1996
- History standards
- NAGB (Box 178)
  - Reauthorization, 1994
  - Members, 1995
  - Marwick, Peat
  - Reading report, 1994
  - Washington Court House, 1996 January 24
  - Standard setting
- AALE (American Academy for Liberal Education)
- NAGB (Box 179)
  - History/Geography Reports, 1994
  - Inclusion
  - New NAEP
  - Achievement levels
  - Nominees
    - 1995
    - 1996
  - Civics
  - Finn membership
  - Congressional Intent and Legislative History
- Incremental Materials (Box 180-208)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described. Contact us at hooverarchivesinfo@stanford.edu